Finding Aid of the UW-Milwaukee Dept. of Psychology Records, 1953-1997
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
UW-Milwaukee Dept. of Psychology Records, 1953-1997
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee. Dept. of Psychology
UWM Archival Collection 114
Accession 2010-068(1)
1 cubic ft. (3 boxes) plus additions of 3 cubic ft. (3 boxes)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Records of the department include correspondence, staff meeting minutes, and miscellaneous information on lectures, undergraduate, and graduate degrees. The correspondence files (1956-1976) largely consist of letters between the dean and associate dean of the College of Letters & Science and the chair of the Department of Psychology, regarding budget concerns, the developments of undergraduate and graduate degrees, staffing, curricula, and department location. The collection also contains materials on the teaching of psychology at County Teacher Colleges of Wisconsin, and a file on a survey course given on the WMVS television station. Also included are the minutes and correspondence of the Joint Department Conference Committee of the Psychology Departments of Madison and Milwaukee (1956-1963).
The Dept. of Psychology was established in 1956 when the University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee was created. Prior to 1956, the predecessor colleges offered psychology courses. Since its inception in 1885, the Wisconsin State Normal School offered general psychology courses as part of its education curricula. After 1927, when the school became the Milwaukee State Normal School, psychology courses were offered under the Department of Education and Psychology. The Dept. of Psychology at UWM began to offer graduate level courses in 1961, offered a full Master of Science in Psychology in 1963, and the Doctorate in Psychology in 1966.
Department Chairs
1956-1961 Herman Weil
1961-1963 Chandler G. Screven
1965-1965 Harry L. Madison
1965-1968 Alan Baron
1968-1971 Eugene H. Eisman
1971-1975 Marilyn E. Miller
1975-1978 Harry L. Madison
1978-1980 John C. Hay
1980-1981 Marilyn E. Miller
1981-1984 Vincent Adesso
1984-1986 Harry L. Madison
1986-1990 John C. Moore
1990-1993 Harry L. Madison
1993-1996 John C. Moore
1996-1997 Harry L. Madison
1997-2003 Raymond Fleming
2003-2006 Rodney A. Swain
2006-2011 David Osmon
2011-2012 James Moyer
2012- Douglas D. Woods
This collection was received in, and is organized in, multiple parts. Additional materials have not been physically or intellectually arranged and interfiled, and researchers may need to consult more than one part of the collection to locate similar materials.
UWM Archival Collection 114: Records, 1953-1989
The collection contains one additional accession.
Accession 2010-068(1): Additions, 1960-1997
Finding aid for accession 2010-068(1) available in the Archives.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
UW-Milwaukee College of Letters & Science Records UWM Archival Collection 1
UW-Milwaukee Dept. of Educational Psychology Records UWM Archival Collection 33
Administrative/Restriction Information
There are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
An unknown donor transferred the collection to the archives prior to 1989. The Department of Psychology donated additional materials in June 2011 (accession 2010-068(1)).
Contents List
- Records, 1953-1989, UWM Archival Collection 114; .8 cubic ft. (2 boxes)
  - Clinical Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1956-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
  - County Teacher's Colleges, 1953, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Departmental Meeting Minutes, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Departmental Meeting Minutes, 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Departmental Meeting Minutes, 1971-1989 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - Executive Committee Meeting Minutes, 1971-1987 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - Graduate Degree Information, Reports and Brochures, 1959-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Joint Department Conference Committee, 1956-1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Lectures, 1957-1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Psychology Newsletter, 1972-1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Report of the Committee on Psychology, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Research Reports, 1970-1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Self-Study Report, 1991-1992 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Television Course, WMVS, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Ten-Year Plan, 1958-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Undergraduate Degree Information, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Additions, 1960-1997, Accession 2010-068(1); 3 cubic ft. (3 boxes); Additions of subject files dating from 1960 to 1997, consisting primarily of accreditation reports and program reviews, as well as planning documents for the department heading into the 21st century. Also included are a few folders of meeting minutes.